Coming up on Plane Crazy Down Under, we're joined by Lockheed Martin F-35 test pilot
Tony Brick-Wilson to discuss his flying career and find out a little about his amazing role.
Every Australian aircraft that has come off of the line, either I or a member of my team
have flown it.
And as this fifth generation jet continues to evolve, Director of F-35 International
Business Development Stephen Over talks about coming upgrades we can expect on RAAF models.
This year we're breaking into production a new computing baseline that will update the
main mission computer on the aircraft, the computer that supports the cockpit displays
and the aircraft memory system.
High flying, high tech, and one of the coolest jobs on earth.
It's all ahead as we get Plane Crazy.
Well hi everyone.
Welcome back to the show.
It's great to have you with us.
This is of course the program where we like to take a look at Australia's aviation industry
and of course aviation all around this part of the world.
I'm Steve Vischer.
Joining me as always is my good friend Grant McGarren.
How are you mate?
Hey, not too bad buddy.
How are you doing?
I'm doing very well and of course really looking forward to this episode.
I'm always doing well when we're about to talk about fast jets and we've got a really
good guest waiting for us who we'll introduce in just a few minutes.
We're going to be covering the F-35 of course which is a maturing platform of course.
We've covered this before.
I remember back to episode 119 Grant when we first started really looking in depth at
the F-35.
I think that was probably back in about 2014 or somewhere around there and it's certainly
become a mature platform these days and a lot has happened and a lot of development
has gone on.
It certainly has mate and the big key phrase that we're hearing again and again is of course
sensor fusion and how the F-35 brings everything together so the pilot doesn't have to build
their situational awareness from multiple screens and inputs from all the different
sensors but the actual platform does it for them.
And mate I think we should get straight on to it because we've got Tony Wilson, Chief
of Fighter Flight Operations at Lockheed Martin on standby.
Should we get straight into it?
Let's do it.
Well g'day Tony.
How are you doing?
Fantastic.
I really appreciate you guys having me on.
I'm really excited about this.
Well Tony we'll kick off with the most important question of all and it's not going to be about
your call sign of brick which we'll also refer to you as but we'll come to that later.
What got you into aviation?
You know I think the story of what got me into aviation is not really different than
any other aviation geek or nerd out there.
We all come from a place and we all have some sort of connection with it.
Mine came from my grandfather.
My grandfather had a love of aviation and from as long as I can remember he used to
take me to the airport and we would watch sit there and watch planes and we would bond
over it.
But I can tell you the moment that was solidified for me of when I would pursue this career
I grew up in South Florida in the early and mid 70s and we took a trip up to Kennedy Space
before the space shuttle had been flying but they had a life-size model of the shuttle
parked outside of the rocket assembly building and I can remember coming around the corner
and looking at this awesome machine and I turned to my teacher and I said hey how do
I get to fly that and she's like well Tony you have to be one of the best test pilots
in the world to get to do that and I was like ah I can do that now I'm not saying I'm the
best test pilot or even I'm a mediocre test pilot at best but that was what really propelled
me into this career.
Because Florida really has a really rich aviation scene there doesn't it I mean there's so much
going on in aviation there it's probably hard not to get hooked if you live there.
Yeah absolutely you have Kennedy Space Center, multiple service bases you know McDill, Homestead,
Loredale International used to actually be a naval air station way back right and you
know pick almost any aerospace industry they've got some presence in Florida absolutely.
So living in Florida you got the bug can you step us through your career to date?
Absolutely so I actually started off my career at the age of 19 I enlisted in the US Navy
and that was a result of me not being the best student coming through high school or
my first attempt at university and the Navy sent me to nuclear power school where I learned
to run nuclear reactors.
I did that for a couple years on a fast attack submarine where I was fortunate enough to
earn a slot in an officer program.
So I went off went back to university did much better this time earning a bachelor's
degree in mechanical engineering and then off to flight school in Pensacola Florida.
I took to fly in you know very naturally I did very well in flight school and earned
a jet slot I went on to jet training which I did in Meridian Mississippi.
Earned my wings of gold and went on to fly the F-18C so did that went through training
to what we call the replacement air group training squadron and then reported to VFA-87
for my first fleet squadron.
While I was with VFA-87 we deployed in support of Operation Iraqi Freedom I was flying off
the USS Roosevelt at the time.
At the completion of that tour again I was fortunate enough to be selected and earn a
slot for Navy test pilot school the Navy sent me off to earn my master's in aeronautical
engineering first and then off to test pilot school I did that for a year.
Upon completion and graduation of test pilot school my first assignment was to work the
F-35 program a very fortunate project coming out of test pilot school brand new test pilot.
I did that for about three years and then returned to the fleet flying F-18F super hornets
forward deployed in Japan off the George Washington.
We lived in Japan for two and a half years and returned back to the test community back
to the F-35 program where I was heavily involved in testing both the F-35B and the F-35C but
primarily the F-35C specifically preparing the aircraft to go to the aircraft carrier
which culminated in me getting to take the F-35C to the USS Nimitz in November of 2014.
I finished up my Navy career in 2016 and was fortunate enough to be hired on or I should
say joined Lockheed Martin as a test pilot and in 2018 I was selected to become the chief
of fighter flight ops still get to fly the F-35 but now I get to lead a fantastic team
of pilots all of the fighter pilots that are currently flying for Lockheed Martin so F-16
F-22 F-35 and whatever special projects that we have come up fantastic.
It's a tough life yeah they let me wear a flight suit to work and I still get to fly
high high performance machines so yeah best of all worlds exactly so a quick side question
then did you have much to do with Billy Flynn yes I know Billy very well.
So Billy and I overlapped at Pax River when I showed up during my second tour as an active
duty Navy pilot he was working for Lockheed at the time so that would have been 2013 we
worked closely together on the F-35 program then and then naturally when I joined Lockheed
Martin I continued to work with Billy until his retirement and I forget the exact date
you know 2018-2019 time frame cool yeah we've had him on the show before I ran into him
at Avalon so I'm hoping to okay we're going to see if we can get him back on he's quite
happy to chat with us again so we obviously didn't scare him off last time but so you've
mentioned that you were primarily on the 35 Bravo and Charlie when you were at the Navy
test pilot but I guess now you're flying all variants aren't you I fly all three variants
at Fort Worth our role here at Fort Worth is to take each and every aircraft as it rolls
off the factory floor and take it airborne for the first time so in this capacity you
know the A model and the C model the A model being the Air Force model conventional takeoff
and landing from runways and the C model the Navy version the CV variant we fly two flights
on each of those the B model the Stovall the hovering aircraft that gets a third flight
but on all three variants the first flight we are primarily checking out the vehicle
systems right is the aircraft built to the quality that we expect and demand from Lockheed
Martin to make sure that we're sending the best aircraft out to you know the war fighters
the men and women that are going to take this into harm's way the subsequent flights are
used to check out our mission systems which that's really where the magic of the F-35
resides in our mission systems and sensor fusion so we want to make sure that that's
all working properly and integrated per design and then like I said that B model gets a third
flight just to check out the Stovall systems. One of the selling points that people like
Billy Flynn have told us about in the past when we've interviewed him is the idea of
making transition into or even variations between the three different variants very
very similar making it easier for the pilot when you're the Stovall aspect of the B model
of course aside are they very different to fly between the three or are they when you
get in is it something that's actually really seamless for you to really adapt to? It's
seamless and I think that's one of the fantastic things that Lockheed Martin did with the F-35
whether I'm in an A a B or a C they all fly almost identical the mission systems are identical so
when I'm employing the aircraft you know I'm solving tactical challenges with it it's the
same right really the big difference is you know how they take off and land and how much
fuel they carry the the A model carries about 18,000 pounds the B model carries about 13,000
pounds you give up some fuel for the lift system and then the C model because of the the larger
wings you get a little extra fuel about 18,000 pounds 19,000 pounds and flying the B model I
mean is is that a heavier aircraft or is is one compensated from the other in terms of less fuel
versus the extra weight of the lift fan? So the the flight control system that our flight
control engineers put into this aircraft it's a really carefree handling so you really don't
notice any shift in CG or really the difference in weight they all fly almost identical you know
and that's that's really a strength because we're already seeing it on the US side with pilot
exchanges Air Force pilots going and flying different variants you know Navy and Marine
Corps pilots flying different variants and then even within you know our allies you know I think
it was just last year we had US Marine Corps B models flying with the Italians off of their
carrier right because it's the same aircraft. So I've been fortunate enough to get into the
cockpit demonstrator that was going around air shows and and you know demonstrations and things
like that and just flying it with that big screen of multi screens made up in front was pretty
amazing but I never got the chance to try an F-35 even a demo helmet to see what it was like from
the inside. How is that transition getting into the the helmet and transitioning into the F-35
what did that what was that like? So the biggest thing that pilots will first notice so I flew
the Gehmics 1 I have not had the opportunity to fly the Joint Helmet Mounted Queuing 2 but I also
believe that's a monocular so I went from a monocular system one projector to a binocular
system in the F-35 helmet so that took a I was surprised that took a little bit of getting used
to training your non-dominant eye to you know take in the symbology. With that being said it's still
a quick transition right so one of the things that pilots will first notice is the F-35 helmet
is probably the most comfortable helmet that a fighter pilot gets because one it's custom fit
to your your head when a pilot is selected to fly the F-35 one of the first things they do is we
send them to what's called the pilot fit facility where they put a latex cap over their over their
head and their head is scanned to map out all the ridges and divots and bumps and you know
irregularities that we all have on our skull fortunately they can't you know there's no
scanning of mental state because it probably would let me fly but but then that information
is sent off your your pads are custom cut they're sent back and then you come back the next day and
you put the helmet on they cut your visor so it's custom fit to you they make sure that there's no
hot spots or whatever you know so little tweaking of the the pads themselves so it's the best-fitting
helmet that I've ever worn you have active noise reduction in the ear cups and so that that's
fantastic you know it's like flying really reduces a lot of the noise but there is a there is a
transition the the pilot will spend the next couple of days tweaking the helmet and exactly
where the displays are to make sure that it is it's zeroed in right because if you compare it to
say you know the jahamics the field of view that is projected is much wider than the field of view
that is projected on an f-35 helmet if there you can see pictures out there where the display the
actual size of the display it's not much larger than the human pupil right and then and that's
by design and that's another reason why the helmet has to fit so good because you can't have this
thing jostling around on your head under G's or or whenever that that symbology has to be available
to you it at all times the symbology is focused for what we call infinity so it's just a seamless
transition as far as when you're flying the symbology overlying with the outside world again
it does take a little bit of getting used to when I first started flying I could actually feel the
muscles in my eyes change as the focal length varied but now you know I've been flying for a
number of years it's it's seamless I don't even notice it anymore okay because yeah you've got
that screen in front of you plus you've also got what's on your on your helmet how do the two
inter interrelate because if you if you look down to look at the screen is the outside view in front
of your pupils or is it only when you're looking up and out no it's it's still there but the the
helmet itself has three different tracking systems it has an inertial tracking system
and has a magnetic tracking system and then it has a visual tracking system with cameras inside
the cockpit so that the aircraft and the aircraft computers are aware of where that the pilots head
in orientation is all time so when I come in to look at the the glass we call it the glass
when come in to look at the glass the symbology is blanked right okay the only time that we won't
blank that symbology is we also have the capability to take the DAS system the six cameras around the
aircraft and project that imagery to the visor and that's really it's it's a useful system during
the day and we'll probably talk a little bit more about that later but as far as pilot visuals it's
used primarily at night this system really turns night into day for the pilot the other advantages
of the the f-35 helmet that you kind of need to get used to is it has your night vision camera
integrated into it so when I'm flying at night I can either turn all the visuals off all the
camera views I can have DAS I can have my night vision camera and I can do it all from the flick
of my thumb on the stick fantastic so that would really change the way you fight the aircraft in
many ways wouldn't it I mean it's all of a sudden it's taking a lot of things that perhaps you had
to give a lot of thought to in in older generation aircraft it seems to me now that you know again
it's it's designed to make things easier and I guess that that leads through to SA and and all
that sort of stuff yeah 100% you know the the helmet is just it's another tool that the pilot
has that helps him or her execute the mission and it's it's the seamless integration of all
the sensors through sensor fusion that's really that that generational leap right so when we talk
about the f-35 and we talk about it being a fifth gen fighter fifth generation fighter most people
automatically think about stealth and stealth is an definitely an important aspect of it you know
the stealth capability that the aircraft brings to the fight it's both an offensive and defensive
capability but really the other part of fifth gen is sensor fusion and what sensor fusion brings
to the pilot so for example when I was flying my fourth gen fighter over Iraq you know the f-18 very
easy aircraft to fly and that's by design but in my legacy f-18 I had to tell the radar where to
look what targets to prioritize I had to interpret what my RWR EW system was displaying to me I had
to prioritize you know what my targeting pod was looking at and more importantly is I had to listen
actively listen to a lot of information that was coming in over the radio to fill in the rest of
the information that was needed and I would build that tactical picture in my head so I was as much a
sensor manager as a tactician you know in my fourth gen aircraft what sensor fusion brings to
the pilot is it's the sensor manager okay it not only does it manage my sensors for me but it
optimizes them depending on what I do mission planning wise on the deck right so f-35 extremely
easy aircraft to fly and again that's by design because that builds in safety margins for the
pilot I'm not too worried about being a sensor manager because I have sensor fusion taking care
of that for me so really what that allows me to do is be that tactician right to quickly analyze
any tactical challenge that's presented to me and we do that via the glass and the PVI and how that
information is presented to the pilot and it allows the pilot to make those split-second tactical
decisions that need to be made to solve any tactical challenge that's out there I've heard
the reference to the f-35 being the quarterback of the mission being up in the air with all that
sensor fusion and calling the shots and giving people information and all that so I'm guessing
that keeps you pretty busy in the cockpit what's it like to be doing that quarterback role in
addition to flying and fighting the aircraft itself so every fighter pilot wants to be the
leader right that's that's just the nature right you know it's I'm the best pilot up here I want
to be in charge but what we're seeing is again if I compare it to you know my fourth gen experience
it would typically take a Navy pilot anywhere between 8 to 12 years of experience before they
got to the point where they could lead in the Navy what we would call you know an LFE or a large
force employment you know taking a large number of aircraft into a contested area and executing
some sort of strike because of sensor fusion and the pilots are achieving that level as early as
two to four years into their career right so I mean it's that's when we talk about generational
leaps you know that's one of the things the services you know training a pilot takes a lot
of resources you know it takes a lot of the country's resources to dedicate to each individual
pilot and they're getting a much better pilot much sooner because of the tools that take some
of the workload off the pilot and allow them to be you know the tactician that you want them to
be so when you talk about you know quarterback in the fight it's one it's it's fun it's exciting
it's a challenge to your professional skills but you know you get up there and the tools that the
aircraft provide you the advanced sensors the sensor fusion as well as the data links that you
know we haven't talked about you know all of this information comes in and is very succinctly displayed
to the pilot so that they're again able to make those quarterback calls and then you bring in you
know the added benefit of these advanced data links that we have link 16 and and metal and
the information that we're bringing in is also pushed out to everybody that we want to share it
with right so even you know the battlefield commanders that may be away from the forward
line where the action is happening they have the same amount of essay that the pilot in the cockpit
has because it's really it's really we hear a lot about this it's being a platform rather than
just an aircraft isn't it like you know this this is this is now changing the way I guess the
battle space is managed because it's it's an integral part of a system rather than just an
individual aircraft or a bunch of individual aircraft so at Lockheed Martin we're working
hard on what we call 21st century security right which is to to bring integrated capability to the
warfighter you know to be able to operate and exploit what we call jato or joint joint all
domain operation so when we talk about 21st century security and jato it's talking about
the integration of space assets air assets both land and sea assets as well as subsurface assets
and each of those entities being able to share information so that they can make the tactical
decision that they need so when we talk about the f-35 yeah it's the f-35 it's a very capable fighter
aircraft but it's also an ISR platform intelligence surveillance and reconnaissance and when you talk
about it in a jato sense or 21st century security sense it's an airborne data node it's about you
know battle management or not battle management but information management because one of the
other aspects I failed to mention when I talked about the aspects of jato right and you know
space air surface subsurface but also cyber right and that's you know having an airborne data node
you know just adds to that capability and that's what the f-35 brings okay so I mean you're you're
sounding like a mini AWACS right there like a small e7 or e3 so how does the f-35 plug in with
those AWACS platforms like in the Navy sense you've got the e2 how does it supplement for the Air
Force talking to the e7 the wedge tail what's what's involved there you're not taking over but
are you able to give them more information than that otherwise have we are just because of the
sensors and the spectrum that our our sensors operate in and again it's because of link 16 and
being able to to pass that information so when you think about it you know if I have you know
a satellite with a certain capability in a certain part of the you know EM spectrum or
visual spectrum or whatever and the f-35 brings a different part of the spectrum you know to the
solution and maybe a ground-based radar you know and we're able to feed all of this information
in and you know it it's a force multiplier is what it is our special guest this week is Tony
Wilson chief of fighter flight operations at Lockheed Martin stick with us folks we'll be
right back after this welcome aboard the high flow media podcast dedicated to sharing the
stories and experiences of the amazing people who make aviation happen from pilots like me to
engineers air traffic controllers and others I'll explore their personal journeys the challenges
and the triumphs they've achieved my name is Damien and I'll be your host whether you're a
seasoned aviation enthusiast or new to the field I invite you to join me as we take off on this
journey of discovery subscribe now on your favorite podcast platform and leave a review
to help spread the word you can find me at highflymedia.com that's h-i-f-l-y media.com
uncovering the people and passion behind aviation one story at a time keeping up to date with the
latest news is a huge part of our daily lives now you can have news on demand with the Australian
Independent Radio news app news and sport in your pocket whenever you want it wherever you are in
the world if you call Australia home you can stay in touch with the air news app download it now for
news on the go this is an this is a news this is a news this is a news Australian Independent
Radio news you're listening to playing crazy down under the show where we talk aviation and our very
special guest this week is Tony Brick Wilson the chief of fighter flight operations at Lockheed
Martin the manufacturer of course of the f-35 Tony I have just one interesting side question there
because I should admit that one of my guilty pleasures is getting on YouTube and watching
cockpit video of carrier ops it just I could watch it all day long I notice when you're talking a lot
there about the ease of use and how much easier this aircraft is to fly I wonder if you could talk
about bringing it onto the boat bring it onto a carrier versus say bring an F you know bring an
F-18 onto the boat there seems to me to be so much going on in that cockpit so many micro
adjustments being made in the Hornet given that this aircraft is an easier aircraft to operate how
does that affect just coming onto the boat it's just a side question because these videos they
just fascinate me so what I can tell you is the f-35 builds huge safety margins into shipboard
operations there's a couple of things that we have going for us in the f-35 and to be fair it's not
just the f-35 the Navy has invested a lot of resources in bringing what the f-35 brings to
the pilot to the Hornet and they're also expanding it out to other aircraft in the fleet but the
f-35 we have what's called Delta flight path and and you're hundred percent right there's you know
multiple micro corrections and inputs while you're trying to land on the ship you know it's the the
task the basic task I can I can break it down into you know the naval aviation mantra is
meatball lineup angle of attack and what that means is you have the Fresno lens that has the
ball off to the left side and the pilots primary task is to keep it between the two green bars
what we call the datums the lineup is to make sure that you are on centerline because the landing
area on an aircraft carrier is not that big and there's aircraft parked on either side of the
landing area so you really can't afford to be you know off by very much and then angle of attack an
angle attack you know it's it's speed well the f-35 takes care of angle attack for you right so I
don't have to worry too much about that and now with Delta flight path it automatically once I'm
on glideslope I can engage it and it will capture and hold that three degree glideslope for me not
only does it do that but normally where the younger pilots will get themselves in trouble is and I
did you know many times trying to come aboard the boat is you get so focused on glideslope that
lineup will fall out of your scan and you'll you'll pick up a drift one way or the other and the LSOs
they'll give you you know a couple seconds to see if you're gonna correct it but if you don't start
to correct it they'll tell you hey you need to come one way or the other and this is normally
where younger pilots would get themselves in trouble because as soon as I now need to make
a lineup correction I may have had the power set perfectly but because I'm changing lift because
I'm changing the drag profile because I'm banking the aircraft now I got to come up on the power and
now I have to reduce the power and then come back up so it's a three-part power correction and then
I got to do it again the other way and normally the pilot becomes so focused on lineup that the
or the glideslope falls out and now they end up having you know multiple corrections to have to
make well Delta flight path and what's called in the F-18 Magic Carpet it helps the pilot out
tremendously because if I start to drift one way or the other all I have to do now is put in
lateral stick input to make that lineup correction and the plane takes care of everything for me it
takes care of the power you know the F-35 has what we call triple ID DLC integrated direct lift so
really what's happening is I'm moving the stick around if I need to change you know I've started
to shallow out or I'm going low and I pull back on the stick actually the control surfaces all
deflect first to change the shape of the wing to change the camber and give me almost immediate
lift so the aircraft heaves back up right so you know whether you're talking about the F-35 and
like I said the Super Hornet has this capability coming back aboard the boat especially during the
day there's so many increased safety margins because of the capability that the digital flight
controls bring to the pilot the other thing that the F-35 pilot has to them is what we call a
ship's reference velocity vector and what that is it's a data link with the ship that actually
takes into account ships motion and now I have a piece of symbology that I'd basically put it on
the deck and that's where I'm gonna land so before when I was flying my legacy Hornet we
had a traditional velocity vector flight path marker so as you came around the corner you know
we made that approach turn during the day you'd use a little bit of Kentucky windage and you'd
put the velocity vector out in front of the ship a little bit and you know you'd you'd game it that
way a little bit but between the the symbology and the flight controls you know it's I won't say it's
easy and I used to say this when I flew you know the legacy Hornet that I would do anything that
the Navy asked me to do for free except land at the boat at night yeah I don't pay anybody enough
money to do that but the tools that we give the pilots now again it makes it easier it makes it
safer which allows them to again focus on the mission and not worry so much about boat operations
I know that's a side question but I tell you we could have a whole separate podcast on carrier
ops because it just those guys the shooters for example they just crack me up with the whole thing
we could have a whole separate podcast on that grant but we should move on absolutely a matter
of fact Ali's price saying don't get them started well let's shift on to a slightly different
question then and you touched on that briefly about the sensor fusion changing how you do
things so how has sensor fusion changed the way you plan and execute missions for example I'll
make a bold statement and say that it hasn't there you go okay because both the US way of
mission planning and prepping for a mission as well as you know our allies we you know we all
share that in common and whether mission planning is always intensive you're analyzing where the
target is what where the threats are what the threats are what are the threats vulnerabilities
to my strengths and how can I exploit that what are my vulnerabilities to the threat if any and
how do I defend against that right so all of that goes into mission planning sensor fusion
increases your mission planning a little bit because you want to put information into the
plane in your mission planning process that's going to bring sensor fusion or optimize sensor
fusion for whatever you're getting ready to whatever tactical challenge you're getting ready
to to go out and and fly against but more importantly it makes things easier in the plane
right so it really doesn't change how I how I mission plan that like I said there's a little
bit extra but the the benefit it brings is flexibility and what I mean by that is if the
scenario doesn't go how I expect it to and 99% of the time the scenarios don't go how you expect
them to there's additional threats or additional capability out there it allows the pilot to change
their game plan on the fly and change that game plan with ease and again it goes back to what I
was saying about you know the difference between taking eight to twelve years to attain a certain
tactical level and attain it now in two to four okay because yeah we all know Von Klauswitz no
plan survives first contact with the enemy and the other one that a wing commander I used to work
with was frequently saying to me was grant have I told you that flexibility wins wars which was
often a signal that he had done something that I needed to correct and fix but yeah those those
two things so yeah I could see what you're meaning there that flexibility that power of information
and ability to adapt is is critical in a especially in a dynamic war environment let alone war but any
environment that we're doing even even a training mission is quite dynamic so fantastic stuff so
I'm gonna go for bring us back into the cockpit and we've got the helmet you've told us a lot
about how that all that all works and how you got the screen the glass as you said how does all this
information get presented to you and and how do you identify key items at various points I imagine
that are you being illuminated by a radar is probably a higher priority than right now than
how much fuel you've got things like that but but how is that presented you see the videos of the
Super Hornets and they've got screens everywhere but you've just got that the glass and the helmet
so let's talk about the glass for just a second it's actually two different displays okay and we
do that for redundancy and safety so that if you lose one display you still have another one but the
glass itself can be broken up into four portals and each of those portals can either have one
display on it or one larger display in two smaller ones I can expand it out so that I've got you know
the display going across two portals right so I have multiple ways that I can configure the glass
for whatever the mission is you think of it like you know an iPad or an iPhone as far as you know
be being having that flexibility additionally the f-35 has five different modes in it we have
navigation air to air one air to air to dogfight and air to surface and each of those five modes
I can set up my displays again however I want it so I set it up on on on deck and matter of fact
we're getting the capability to actually set it up in mission planning so the pilot doesn't even
need to worry about setting it up on deck so the displays are already optimized for your mode and
your mode is tied to whatever your task is and it's obviously in the name of the mode right so air
to air one air to air two I'm doing some sort of air to air mission dogfight you know I'm mixing
it up and air to surface I'm executing I'm prosecuting a target on the ground now whether
you're talking about you know the glass and you know the f-35 and a fifth-gen fighter or you know
any of the other fourth-gen fighters out there one of the first tasks that a pilot needs to learn is
their scan where am I looking for what information and when yep yeah right so it because it's it
does me no good to be looking at my t-flare imagery if I'm trying to figure out you know
from you know EW or energy waves coming off an aircraft you know to help me identify it so it's
a matter of learning where to look and and when to look and again technology is is advancing right
and there's systems out there they're not in the f-35 yet it's you know still being tested on you
know multiple different helmets out there but not only you know I have a camera a mission replay
camera in the helmet so I know where the pilot's head is looking but here in the near future not
only are we going to know where the pilot's head is looking but we're going to know where the
pilot's eyes are looking and that's just going to aid in that training aspect right so the
instructor pilots are going to have the capability to come back and be like oh yeah your your head
was in the right place but you were looking in the wrong place right so it's a matter of learning
what to scan and and when to scan it and that just comes with training and experience yeah we
starting to see that in simulators now where they're doing the eye tracking while you're in
the sim so yeah no no huge surprise to hear that's going to wind up in the helmet as well
yeah so in terms of maturity of the platform I mean it's been under development now for many
many years how does how does Lockheed Martin see it going now are we are we in a in a spot where
we're happy obviously there's a process of continued improvement but where does the company see the
evolution of the aircraft as we sit here in 2023 so the the f-35 that's flying today is not the
same f-35 that was flying in 2010 okay one of the great strengths of the f-35 is it is a software
driven aircraft okay what do I mean by that when I was flying my fourth gen fighter you would get a
software update about every two years okay and with that software update came incremental
increases in capability but for real capability increases you had to change out boxes that came
in hardware changes we're in the process of doing tr3 tech refresh 3 this is only the third time
in the history of the aircraft that we are actually changing out hardware and we're doing
it because computer processing power has gotten better sensors have gotten better right and when
you compare that two-year software update cycle to what we push out now which is about every six
months yep right and again with each new software comes new capability so when I say that the
aircraft that's flying today resembles nothing of the aircraft that flew back in 2010 I'm talking
about the tactical capability that the aircraft had because of all the software updates that have
come along the way and now the third time that we're actually refreshing the hardware so when
you talk about you know what does the plane look like in 2040 what does the plane look like in 2070
the only answer I can give you is I don't know but I can't wait to see it right because I know
the new capabilities that are coming right around the corner you know as well as you know the future
capabilities that you know Lockheed's working on Lockheed Martin's working on and as a tactical
aviator I am excited to see what comes next yeah obviously there's so many of these aircraft flying
around the world these days I suppose it goes without saying that you're getting constant
feedback from of all different types from all around the world on different tweaks you might
like to make absolutely so one of the decisions that was made in the program early on was to use
this idea of concurrency so what do I mean by that when aircraft specifically tactical aircraft
went through you know their design and field process you know prior to the f-35 and you know
earlier they went through distinct phases they went through you know first the aircraft was built
some prototypes were built and they went through developmental tests DT and in that time period
you know test pilots such as myself we flew it we identified you know challenges and tweaks
you know we put them in we tested them out we're like okay yes it is past developmental flight
test now it's ready for operational tests and then we would send it on to operational tests and
the operational testers would do their thing right and then they again they'd identify challenges
and you know things that needed to be addressed it would get fixed and then it was sent finally
sent on to the fleet the end user where they would eventually ioc declare ioc or initial
operating capability the f-35 program went with this idea of concurrency and i can tell you as
a developmental flight or a developmental test pilot at first it was a little bit frustrating
because i was doing developmental tests in the aircraft's portion you know we weren't done
you know carving out the full envelope and we already had operational tests going on as well as
the services flying it operationally and the reason i say it was a little bit of a challenge
is because you know the the fleet pilot would come back or like well this doesn't work we're
like yes we know and and we're working we're working on it right but i i think my my personal
feeling now is that we have a much more robust system uh in the aircraft because of uh this
idea of concurrency because we got the end users involved in the design process if you will so
early so you know instead of you know an idea taking legs and running and then making it out
to the fleet and the fleet pilots being like i'm never going to use this why would you design it
that way they were able to identify that earlier right so and it's not just the u.s uh services
it's every nation that's been part of the program whenever they come onto the program
you know they start integrating into these processes that we have to help develop the
aircraft and make sure that when i make the statement that the f-35 is the most capable
the most survivable uh the most connected fighter flying on the face of the planet today i can say
that with confidence because i have however many pilots and country services to back that
statement up yep and uh for instance you've got a curl the australian canadian uk uh reprogramming
lab which uh yeah that's a major thing that's going on in the u.s at the moment where these
non-us five eyes groups are doing their their specific programming to help develop so that does
lead into the question the one that we're being from down under that we've got to ask is uh have
you had much to do with the the raf both personnel and aircraft and so on have you tested any of our
aircraft have you engaged a lot with australian personnel so uh i'll answer that in two two parts
um every australian air aircraft that has come off of the the line either i or a member of my
team have flown it so um as far as integration and interaction um with the australians
unfortunately uh no i haven't as a matter of fact um it's still on my to-do list to actually make it
down to australia i was in i was in the u.s navy we were doing an exercise in australia down in uh
tindle and uh it's actually that's that's where i earned my mission commander qual that you know
leading uh large forces uh you know into tactical scenarios and we were uh supposed to stop in
australia and i was super excited this was going to be my first time and the port call got cancelled
oh no so heartbreaking i've flown over uh i've flown over your country i've uh i've dropped um
you know practice ordinance on uh on your ranges but i've never had the opportunity to actually
come down and enjoy the culture well we need to rectify that i think absolutely i will have to
talk we will have to have a chat with ali at the end of this uh this recording
uh
so tony just as we uh come to the end of our time here um we never got around to asking you about
your call sign brick and of course we have to ask every fighter pilot uh that we come across
say how they came across their call sign and can you give us the pg version yeah the pg version
yeah yeah yeah this this does go out to radio and kids so absolutely so unfortunately um you
probably can't tell from uh from the video but i'm a relatively short uh pilot uh short and stout
in nature so uh the call sign brick especially in my younger years was very fitting to uh my
build as well as my personality uh you know small dense uh rough around the edges uh i could be
abrasive uh trying to get me to change uh my mind on anything uh was like pushing on a brick wall
because uh some people say i have a tendency to be stubborn i disagree but uh the uh the other uh
the other story again with uh being short uh we carry uh basically an external hard drive
from mission planning out to the jet uh and we call that uh the brick so one of the running
jokes was how many bricks did i have to sit on so i could see outside the cockpit oh such a cruel
industry oh it is it is you gotta have thick skin oh yeah and not just for the debriefs
well brick thank you so much for coming on the show this has been awesome uh really appreciate
you taking the time and very conscious of the fact that we're almost at 7 pm on a friday evening
your time so that bourbon is just around the corner because we're going to wrap it here
absolutely hey i had uh a lot of fun you know if i can't be uh flying then talking about it's the
next best thing so i really appreciate the opportunity thank you look let's be honest sir
we've all got to eat that we do kevin food is such a big part of life isn't it and talking about
food can lead us to all sorts of places and all sorts of people yep and every week on the food
bites podcast we catch up with someone who might be a tv celebrity a high-profile sports star
a politician could be anyone and we talk to them about food their kitchen skills or you know
sometimes lack of uh life and and love and kevin every week there's the friday food poll oh yes
now that is food bites with sarah paterson and me kevin hillier you can find us wherever you
find your favorite podcast and of course every sunday morning at nine o'clock on the ace radio
network you're listening to plane crazy down under the show where we like to talk aviation and we
certainly love to talk about fighter jets in fact grant this week we're talking about the f-35
and back at uh avalon earlier in the year of course uh lockmart had a pretty uh big presence
there in the f-35 of course uh you know it was the jet that's taking everybody's attention
their director of international business development for the jet is stephen over
and he joined us for an interview on our our sister program can we call it that grant the
australian defense magazine podcast and we had a great chat with him the fine folks of the
australian defense magazine podcast allow us to use some of their content once it's been out on
their show for a bit here's a few excerpts of the key pieces that fit in with what tony was talking
about before we're incorporating an upgrade that we call block four so block four will span about
a seven or eight year time frame and it starts with some fairly significant hardware upgrades
to our mission systems or avionics as we call it this year we're breaking into production a new
computing baseline that will update the main mission computer on the aircraft
the computer that supports the cockpit displays and the aircraft memory system
and that creates a computing infrastructure that then we can leverage with future software upgrades
we're also incorporating a next-gen distributed aperture system this infrared camera that's
positioned around the airplane that allows the pilot to see hemispherically and infrared
and that new sensor it was it was principally put on the airplane to reduce cost and be
more supportable but it's going to have about a 2x improvement in detection range and detection
performance it's just a benefit of modern technology what pilot wouldn't love that
yeah and so that that starts the foundation australia's last nine airplanes that are
delivered this year will have that hardware baseline and then incrementally year over year
there's new software upgrades that will bring new weapons additional sensor modes and other
performance features that will keep this airplane at the cutting edge state-of-the-art military
capability so that australia the u.s and our allies will have the ability to deter aggression
from the adversaries that are out there for decades to come that's fantastic and will the
you mentioned that the last few will have that hardware capability is that plan to be
progressively applied to the existing fleets when they come in for major upgrades and it
absolutely is there's already a plan that we and the f-35 joint program office have worked with
the australian air force to factor their airplanes into a depot mod program at rdaf williamtown
and over the coming years their airplanes will all be upgraded to this common block four baseline
let's touch on sensor fusion well as an engineer i can tell you sensor fusion is
probably the most advanced state-of-the-art feature of the f-35 and i've you know focused on how do
you describe to people that aren't fighter pilots what sensor fusion is and the way i would relate
it is you have to contrast it with what a pilot that flies a fourth generation airplane is doing
versus a pilot that's flying the f-35 so the pilot that's flying a fourth generation airplane
the australian air force has some of the finest fourth generation airplanes in the world
with both classic and super horse guess the classics have been retired
um we produce one of the finest fourth generation airplanes also in the world the f-16 fighting
falcon great fourth-gen airplane right and so the pilot instinctually he knows how to fly the
airplane he doesn't have to think about how to control and maneuver the aircraft that's just
instinctual for it and so he has a dedicated display for each and every sensor he has in the
cockpit he has a radar and a dedicated display that shows him radar targeting he'll have electronic
warfare and a dedicated display that shows him what his electronic warfare system is seeing
and if he has the luxury of an infrared tracking system or some kind of infrared
detection system he may have a third display that shows him what that's that sensor is seeing and
most of his mental capacity is spent trying to glue it in his mind what each of these three
or four displays are showing him into a three-dimensional picture of the battle space
with f-35 we've taken the power of modern computing and almost nine million lines of
software source code and we've automated that functionality for the pilot so what he sees when
he sits in the cockpit is this large panoramic cockpit display it's about the size of two large
ipads and he'll typically have half of it dedicated to something we call a tactical situation display
it's this god's eye view of the battle space and he doesn't worry about individual sensors
any longer he doesn't worry about a radar he doesn't worry about electronic warfare he doesn't
worry about infrared it just all logically appears on his cockpit display and he never
has to worry about it as he's approaching the battle space he'll set range scales and targets
just magically appear pilots that have transitioned from fourth generation airplanes into f-35 they
will also tell you one of the things that's the biggest surprise to them not only is how well
sensor fusion tells you where everything is in the battle space but how well the intrinsic features
in the airplane also derive combat id yeah powerful powerful performance from it from the
airplane right so you not only know typically where everything is in the battle space but for
the most part you know what everything is as well yeah and so if you're flying the airplane
it's a significant workload reducer you're not trying to create a mental image of the battle
space you have this very logical view and so the pilot becomes a tactician and what we're seeing
as this airplane is being put in the hands of seasoned military pilots is even young first
lieutenant second lieutenants that have just transitioned to the f-35 are able to be battle
space commanders because they have the bandwidth they have they have the omniscience of what's
happening in the battle space they're making fourth generation airplanes better that are
collaborating with them well there you go and of course grants you can find the full interview
there in episode 42 of the australian defense magazine you can find that at australiandefense.com.au
and we do thank them for allowing us to use that audio in this program of course we do very proudly
produce that program on their behalf so it's always great to be able to you know get some
content out and run it in this show as well fantastic certainly is mate and a lot of fun
producing the australian defense magazine podcast as well but it does cover more than just aviation
but i think this episode has been chuck full of of content as our friends in the us would like to
say and it's probably time we start looking at wrapping this one up we do indeed thanks very
much for joining us of course we'd love to hear what you think about the f-35 lots of people have
lots of things to say about it we certainly hope that programs like this allow people to get a
much more detailed view on just what's going into that jet and some of the amazing technology
internet it really is amazing contact at plane crazy down under.com is where you can drop us
a line and we'd certainly love to hear from you on all sorts of topics about aviation we'll keep
the posty away from the mailbox this week because time is a little bit against us but we'd certainly
love to hear from you thanks very much for joining us thanks to lockheed martin for providing us with
the opportunity to get these interviews we really do appreciate it grant we'll be back with another
episode very very shortly yeah i think you're right there mate and there's some great content
already recorded some just about to be recorded and oh lots more in the queue we'll be back very
soon of course the gold coast pacific air show has just been run as we as we record this one we'll
have a wrap-up of that show in the next episode so keep an eye on the feed steve visher and grant
mcheron wishing you very safe flying folks and we'll talk to you again very soon find show notes
for this episode along with our contact details and a full back catalogue of shows
at plane crazy down under.com drop us a line anytime with feedback story suggestions or
advertising inquiries we'd love to hear from you title music is you name it by brian simpson
plane crazy down under is a southern skies media production
southern skies media